{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This event ended when acting governor Thomas Hutchison promised a fair investigation into this event if the crowd watching the event dispersed. This event is depicted in a famous engraving by Paul Revere. John Adams defended eight soldiers involved in this event that led to the death of a black dockworker named Crispus Attucks. For ten points, name this 1770 event in which British soldiers fired on a crowd, killing five unarmed citizens in the capital of Massachusetts.",
      "answer": "Boston Massacre A"
    },
    {
      "question": "In front of this structure while standing in a bucket crane, David Hasselhoff performed his hit song “Looking for Freedom” before thousands of activists in 1989. Peter Fechter was shot and killed along the “death strip” of this structure by guards on one side. A country on one side of this structure referred to it as the Anti-Fascist Protection Rampart. For ten points, name this structure which Ronald Reagan asked Mikhail Gorbachev to tear down while it still divided a German city.",
      "answer": "Berlin Wall"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Battle of Meloria began the decline of this city-state in favor of Genoa. This city had become powRerful through the sacking of Palermo in 1063 and by helping drive the Saracens from Sardinia in 1016. Located on the Arno, six miles from the Ligurian Sea, this city was once considered the main port in Tuscany and is noted for its inclined campanile, or “leaning tower.” For ten points, name this Italian city.",
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man built a line of fortifications around Alesia to defeat Vercingetorix and demanded that his pirate captors ransom him for a higher sum of money. The phrase “the die is cast” was uttered by this lover of Cleopatra before he crossed the Rubicon. This man’s assumption of extraordinary powers was Dopposed by Cassius and Brutus. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate and Roman dictator who was assassinated on the Ides of March.",
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jean Gerson helped resolve a crisis in this organization by rejecting two candidates to lead it, while Emperor John VIII joined the Council of Ferrara-Florence to seek the aid of this organization. This organization was based out of Avignon with the support of Philip IV, but it moved back to its original home after the Council of Constance. This organization split with its Eastern counterpart in 1054 after an excommunication from the Ecumenical Patriarch. For ten points, name this organization headed by the Pope in Rome.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 13-Point Program was issued by people of this nationality who founded the Chicago-based Young Lords. At the Blair House, two people of this nationality carried out a failed assassination attempt on Harry Truman. The citizenship rights for people of this nationality were granted in the Jones-Shafroth Act. By 1950, over 60,000 of these people lived in an area close to 110th Street in New York that became F known as Spanish Harlem. For ten points, what is this nationality given to people from an American island Commonwealth in the Caribbean.",
      "answer": "Puerto Rican"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one of these events, a man claims that he’ll “watch the blood flow” before asking another man “now who’s got that red coat.” In another of these events, one man claims that he “shook hands with both Ronalds / Reagan and McDonald’s” before telling Vladimir Putin and Joseph Stalin that that they need A a shower. Abraham Lincoln slaps Donald Trump in his appearance in one of these events, which usually involve characters played by EpicLLOYD and NicePeter. For ten points, name these lyrical contests that make up a popular series on YouTube.",
      "answer": [
        "Epic Rap Battles of History",
        "ERB"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This agreement was formulated after one country’s failure to recapture Saint-Domingue in a slave revolt. The U.S. president behind this agreement sent Robert Livingston and James Monroe to negotiate it. That president later sent Lewis and Clark on an expedition examining the territorial gains from this agrReement. For ten points, name this agreement under Thomas Jefferson that procured a large section of what is now the United States from France.",
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events was witnessed by John Joseph Henry while imprisoned on the HMS Pearl in New York Harbor in 1776. A shed on DeKoven Street was supposedly the first building destroyed in an 1871 event of this type, which allegedly began when Mrs. O’Leary’s cow overturned a lantern. In 2020, the most damaging event of this type in U.S. history destroyed more than 4.4 million acres. For ten points, Dname these events, one of which caused much of Chicago to burn.",
      "answer": "Wildfires"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person served in the Auxiliary Territorial Service during World War Two and was harshly criticized for being “out of touch” by John Grigg after the Suez Crisis. The term “annus horribilis” was used by this figure to describe a year in which two of her three children’s marriages ended and a fire broke out in Windsor Castle. This figure’s eldest child separated from his spouse due to Camilla Parker-Bowles. That son was Charles, the Prince of Wales. For ten points, name this longest reigning British monarch.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth II T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city, a lawyer named Theodore Landsmark was attacked with an American flag in a Pulitzer Prize-winning photo titled The Soiling of Old Glory.FROAR was an organization created in response to the 1974 desegregation of schools in this city. During a 1969 Moratorium to End the War in Vietnam, over 100 thousand protestors gathered in this city’s namesake Common. Occupy protests in this city were covered by reporters for its Globe newspaper. For ten points, name this capital of Massachusetts.",
        "answer": "Boston, Massachusetts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The tallest building in Boston, and New England, is a tower named for this Governor of Massachusetts, president of the Second Continental Congress, and signer of the Declaration of Independence. A",
        "answer": "John Hancock"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was recognized in the Treaty of Le Goulet, though he later lost the battle of Bouvines to its other signatory, Philip Augustus. This man refused to recognize Stephen Langton as Archbishop of Canterbury,leadingInnocentIIItoexcommunicatethismanin1209.AfterhewascorneredatRunnymede by disgruntled nobles, this man was forced to sign a document that outlined principles such as “habeas corpus.” For ten points, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta in 1215. R",
        "answer": [
          "John",
          "John Lackland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John succeeded this brother, with a notably valiant nickname, as king after he was killed suppressing a revolt in France.",
        "answer": [
          "Richard I",
          "Richard the Lionhearted",
          "Richard Coeur de Lion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Missouri Bootheel was the main area affected by one of these events that began at 2 A.M. on December 16, 1811. That event of this type was interpreted by some Native Americans as a sign that they D should support Tecumseh’s War. Occurring in the New Madrid [MAD-rid], zone that event was the most powerful event of this type east of the Rocky Mountains. For ten points, name these seismic events.",
        "answer": "Earthquakes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "131 people died in 1964 from various effects caused by the largest earthquake in U.S. history whose epicenter was 12 miles north of Prince William Sound in this U.S. state.",
        "answer": "Alaska T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Oliver Tambo as head of his political party. This leader was critical of the “unspeakable atrocities” of the U.S. and called for the Lockerbie bomber’s sentence to be served in Libya. In one famous speech, this co-founder of the “Spear of the Nation” declared that he was “prepared to die” during the Rivonia trial. The Truth and Reconciliation commission was opened by this man after being F freed from Robben Island by F.W. De Klerk. For ten points, name this president of the ANC, opponent of apartheid, and the first black president of South Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "Nelson Mandela",
          "Madiba"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ANC was founded in 1912 with the mission to bring people from their continent together as one people including full voting rights and the end of apartheid. For what does the acronym “ANC” stand?",
        "answer": "African NationAal Congress"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s last words noted that a rooster was owed to Asclepius, after this man’s prior refusal to save himself served as the basis for the dialogue “Crito.” This man, who described himself as a “gadfly,” was depicted by Jacques-Louis David drinking hemlock shortly after he faced trial for corrupting the youth of Athens. For ten points, name this philosopher, the teacher of Plato, who quoted this man in his Apology saying, “the unexamined life is not worth living.”",
        "answer": "Socrates R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Plato’s Apology, a story is told that this oracle, the high priestess of the Temple of Apollo, said that there was no one wiser than Socrates.",
        "answer": [
          "Oracle of Delphi",
          "Pythia"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1816 Frederick Fidfaddy novel was the first to use the name of this figure in its most popular connotation. This figure was inspired by a meatpacker from Troy, New York who worked hard to provide adequate rations for soldiers during the War of 1812. The original “Yankee Doodle” song makes reference D to this figure, whose outfit was likely inspired by that of Brother Jonathan. Thomas Nast was the first to draw cartoons of this allegorical figure whom James Montgomery Flagg depicted in war recruiting posters saying “I want you.” For ten points, name this top hat-wearing figure who allegorically represents the United States.",
        "answer": "Uncle Sam"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to popularizing Uncle Sam, Thomas Nast also created this symbol of the Grand Old Party.",
        "answer": "Republican Elephant T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of this actor’s films, Harlen Maguire is tasked with assassinating this actor’s character, Michael Sullivan, an Irish mobster in Depression-era Illinois. In another film, this man fires a pistol repeatedly at an approaching tank when the tank is suddenly bombed from above. This actor in the 2002 film Road to Perdition, commands the 2nd Ranger Battalion in a film which opens with the landing at Normandy. In F that film, this man play Captain John Miller, whose men are tasked with finding a missing paratrooper. For ten points, name this actor who starred in Saving Private Ryan.",
        "answer": "Tom Hanks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In this 1995 film, Tom Hanks plays astronaut Jim Lovell who commanded the namesake mission that failed to land on the moon but successfully returned to earth.",
        "answer": "Apollo 13 A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this man’s reign, 24 carriage loads of Jewish manuscripts were burned after his court presided over a disputation known as the “Trial of the Talmud.” This man dispatched William of Rubruck to the Golden Horde in an attempt to garner support. Though this son of Blanche of Castile captured Damietta, he was defeated at Al Mansurah shortly afterward by the Mamelukes. This man’s subsequent leadership of the Eighth Crusade ended when he died of dysentery in 1270. For ten points, name this man, the only king of France canonized by the Catholic church.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis IX",
          "Saint Louis R"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis IX died in this modern North African country, bordered by Algeria and Libya, the northernmost country in Africa.",
        "answer": "Republic of Tunisia"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "New Deal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who instituted the New Deal in the first 100 days of his administration F",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic crisis beginning in 1929 that the New Deal attempted to address",
          "answer": "Great Depression"
        },
        {
          "question": "Program to provide economic development to the namesake river valley",
          "answer": [
            "Tennessee Valley Authority",
            "TVA A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Program that acknowledged a basic right to old age pensions and unemployment insurance",
          "answer": "Social Security"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency that conducted public works and employed artists in Federal Project Number One",
          "answer": [
            "Works Progress Administration",
            "WPA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency created by the National Industrial Recovery Act to reduce competition, symbolized by a blue eagle R",
          "answer": "National Recovery Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname given to a group of Supreme Court justices who opposed it",
          "answer": "Four Horsemen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Still-functioning agency established to protect money deposited into a bank",
          "answer": [
            "Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation",
            "FDIC D T Scotland"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Scotland...",
      "prompt": "Name the scotland......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was united with Wales and this other country to form the Kingdom of Great Britain F",
          "answer": "England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has its capital at this city",
          "answer": "Edinburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Contains some native speakers of this indigenous language descended from Ancient Irish",
          "answer": "Gaelic A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Treaty of Perpetual Peace with this English king, the first Tudor monarch",
          "answer": "Henry VII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought its first war of independence under this knight, who won the Battle of Stirling Bridge",
          "answer": "Sir William Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was also known as the Kingdom of this name, which follows “Duke of” in a Spanish noble title.",
          "answer": "Alba R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took control of these inner and outer island chains from the Vikings in the Treaty of Perth",
          "answer": "Hebrides"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was ruled in the 11th century by two kings of this name, including Macbeth’s predecessor",
          "answer": "Duncan D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuba",
      "prompt": "In the history of the island of Cuba, name the",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country which colonized it and held it for more than 400 years until 1898 F",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Cuba, also its largest city",
          "answer": [
            "Havana",
            "La Habana"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American warship whose sinking in Cuba led to the outbreak of the Spanish American War.",
          "answer": "USS Maine A"
        },
        {
          "question": "American military base and prison on the Southeastern coast of Cuba.",
          "answer": "Guantanamo Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Secretary of Cuba’s Communist Party for 50 years",
          "answer": "Fidel Castro"
        },
        {
          "question": "U2 Pilot Rudolf Anderson was the only pilot fatality in this 1962 crisis in Cuba",
          "answer": [
            "Cuban Missile Crisis",
            "October Crisis of 1962 R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Southwest African nation to which Cuba sent troops in its 1975 war of independence",
          "answer": "Angola"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Cuba, a former engineer who succeeded Raul Castro in that position in April, 2018",
          "answer": "Miguel Diaz-Canel D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This seven-word phrase ended a speech that prompted Edward Carrington to ask to be buried on the spot. This phrase appeared in a sFpeech whose speaker claims to have “but one (20 pts)",
        "lamp by which my feet are guided; and that is the lamp of experience.” This phrase’s first published appearance was in a biography of its Virginia-born speaker by William Wirt. Its orator said this phrase in a speech addressed to Peyton Randolph during a (10 pts)",
        "1775 convention held in Williamsburg. For ten points, name this famous exclamation delivered by Patrick Henry."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "“Give me liberty,",
        "give me death!” A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alex Kershaw’s book The Bedford Boys chronicled the story of Company A of the 116th Infantry, which suffered heavy losses during this battle. Operation Fortitude South sought to convince the defenders that George Patton’s First United States Army Group would target (20 pts)",
        "Pas-de-Calais instead of the objective of this operation. James Rudder’s Army Rangers suffered heavy losses while storming the (10 pts)",
        "cliffs of Pointe-du-Hoc during this battle. Five beachheads were established at Sword, Gold, Juno, Utah, and Omaha during this battle. For ten points, name this June 6, 1944 Allied invasion of Normandy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "D-Day",
        "Operation Overlord,",
        "Battle of Normandy before it is mentioned R"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event occurred on the same day that Annie Leibovitz took a photo of its central figure curled up naked next to his clothed wife. The perpetrator of this action was caught holding a copy of The Catcher in the Rye. The (20 pts)",
        "victim was returning to the Dakota apartment complex from the Record Plant Studio. The song “All My Loving” came over emergency room speakers at a hospital just as the victim of this event died. A portion of Central Park called (10 pts)",
        "Strawberry Fields was created after this event, which was carried out by Mark Chapman. Yoko Ono became a widow after, for ten points, what event that resulted in the death of a Beatle? D"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Murder of John Lennon",
        "assassination",
        "other equivalents to murder of John Lennon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The second of these conflicts featured Barcids fighting on three fronts, including two sons of Hamilcar. The loser of the third of these conflicts was raided by (20 pts)",
        "Numidians and fell after a three-year siege under Scipio Aemilianus. The second of these conflicts was a sixteen year long campaign that ended at the Battle of Zama. Cato the Elder ended every speech advocating for the destruction of (10 pts)",
        "Rome’s enemy in these wars. For ten points, name this series of wars between Rome and Carthage."
      ],
      "answer": "Punic Wars T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Abraham Curry is considered the founder of this city, where he served as the first superintendent of its Mint. This city’s Ormsby House is a casino that was named for a major who was killed in the (20 pts)",
        "Pyramid Lake War. The first branch of the Virginia and Truckee Railroad connected Virginia City with this city, which grew considerably during the F Comstock Lode. This city’s namesake also names a (10 pts)",
        "subrange of the Sierra Nevada and was a fur trapper who served as the guide for John Fr´emont. For ten points, name this capital city of Nevada."
      ],
      "answer": "Carson City, Nevada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man may have devised a ship to collapse on itself in an attempt to assassinate his mother. This man sent Corbulo to the East after the Parthians attempted to place Tiridates on the throne of Armenia, while his general (20 pts)",
        "Suetonius was responsible for suppressing A the revolt of Boudicca. This man poisoned Britannicus to secure power, though he himself (10 pts)",
        "committed suicide, beginning the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this emperor who was said to have fiddled as Rome burned."
      ],
      "answer": "Nero"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his History of the World in Six Glasses, Tom Standage notes how the first venue at which this good was sold in Damascus was established in 1530. Legends claim that an Ethiopian named Kaldi discovered the major (20 pts)",
        "effects of this good after his goats conRsumed it. A Red Sea port in Yemen that extensively traded this good lends its name to one of its most common types today. Sufis allegedly used this substance while performing rituals that required them to (10 pts)",
        "stay awake for long periods. For ten points, name this substance whose variations include Ristretto, Turkish, and Cappuccino."
      ],
      "answer": "Coffee"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a battle for this city, sniper fire killed General Robert Ross, who turned command over to Arthur Brooke moments before dying. The Battle of North Point was fought in this Dcity, and a naval attack on this city (20 pts)",
        "inspired a lawyer who had negotiated the release of William Beanes to write a poem that was later set to the (10 pts)",
        "tune of “To Anacreon in Heaven.” For ten points, name this Maryland city that was defended by Fort McHenry in the War or 1812, whose bombing inspired the writing of “The Star Spangled Banner.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Baltimore T"
    }
  ]
}